Okay, today's דף daf *daf* is יג *Yud Gimmel*, thirteen. I just
also want to start by again saying that we are continuing of
course to pray and to dedicate the דף *daf* for the safe
return of the three Israeli boys, teenagers. There's going to be a
gathering today at 42nd and second Avenue, a mass gathering of many
many organizations, חובבי תורה Torah, *Hovevei Torah* included, so at 12 o'clock
to pray and to demonstrate for the for the return of the
of the boys, so if anybody's able to make it at that
time that would be greatly
appreciated and very meaningful, as we've been of course learning the idea
of being part of public prayer and participating in the צער *tzar*
of the ציבור tzibbur *tzibur*, which is obviously a theme we're about
to continue today. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues and we're a
little bit behind, we pick up on יב עמוד ב *Yud Bet
Amud Bet*, where it says like this. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב
*Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav*, line starts the third רב *Rav* is
about 20 lines down on יב עמוד ב *Yud Bet Amud Bet*.
So we had a whole discussion before about again this issue of
תענית ציבור tanis tzibur *Ta'anit Tzibur*, which while you can have a
תענית ציבור taanit tzibbur, *Ta'anit Tzibur* that starts in the day and
doesn't have all the additional demonstrations of of fasting or of denial,
the wearing of the shoes etc, but תענית ציבור ta'anit tzibur. *Ta'anit
Tzibur* as a concept means starting the night before, not bathing, not
having sex, not wearing shoes etc, and that that basically does not
occur in בבל *Bavel* because of the lack of concern of rain
with the one exception of תשעה באב Tisha B'Av *Tisha B'Av*. So
that was a recent discussion about people that would not wear shoes
would still want to wear shoes because it really wasn't a תענית
ציבור ta'anit tzibur, *Ta'anit Tzibur* even though obviously the community was fasting
it didn't have that weight and again once again touching on this
issue about יחיד *yachid* and רבים *rabbim* and how one participates in
that communal practice. Okay, so now we go back though because the
recurring theme here has been the private תענית ta'anis *ta'anit*, and so
we return for this for a little bit before we hit the
next משנה Mishnah. *mishna*. So let's take a look. We've already learned
that a private תענית ta'anis. *ta'anit* has the קבלה מבעוד יום kabbala
mibod yom *kabbalah mibe'od yom*, the statement of שמואל Shmuel. *Shmuel*. We've
also learned a statement that the private תענית ta'anis. *ta'anit* has to
go till the end of the day, that was the discussion of
תענית ta'anis. שעות *ta'anit sha'ot*, and now we have this final point.
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב *Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav* לוה loveh.
אדם תעניתו ופורע *loveh adam ta'anito upore'a*. A person can borrow his
תענית tanis *ta'anit* and pay it back. So you a person accepted
upon himself to fast and this came up also the other day
when it came to the issue of encountering a one of the
days of that were on מגילת תענית tanis *Megillat Ta'anit* that you
don't fast on that day but maybe you pay it off in
a different day that this sort of in a way makes it
makes the fast like a thing that you have that you owe
and the very language here of you can borrow and pay back.
So you can borrow against it, I'll eat today I'll pay back
the תענית tanis *ta'anit* tomorrow. If something comes up you don't you
can do it not on the day you originally designated but on
a different day. כי אמריתה קמיה דשמואל *Ki amritai kammei d'Shmuel*, when
I said it to שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*, אמר לי *amar li* he
said to me, וכי נדר neder קיבל עליה דלא סגי דלא מצער
נפשיה *vechi neder kibal alei d'lo sagi d'lo matzre nafshia*? I don't
get it. Is is this some type of of a vow that
it wouldn't be enough I'm sorry דלא סגי דלא משלם mishalem *d'lo
sagi d'lo m'shalem* that it wouldn't be enough if he didn't actually
fulfill his vow? לצעורי נפשיה קיבל עליה *Letzarei nafshia kibal alei*. He
just decided that he wanted to undergo accept some suffering upon himself,
some self-denial. אי מצי מצער נפשיה *Im matzei m'tzarei nafshia*, so if
he can do it יישר כח *Yashar Koach*. אי מצי *Im matzei*
if he's able to מצער נפשיה *m'tzarei nafshia*. אי לא מצי *Im
lo matzei* if he's not able to לא מצער נפשיה *lo m'tzarei
nafshia*. He won't do it. Now that's quite shocking because that basically
means that שמואל *Shmuel* says there's no binding nature of a private
תענית tanis? *ta'anit*. If you have you want to fast you you
say you want to spend the day not eating because the day
then if you do it great if not if you're not able
to do it okay you had a good intent it was all
very lovely but there's no like binding nature that we have to
talk about borrowing and paying back and it's not a נדר neder
*neder*. Of course remember that it was exactly שמואל *Shmuel* that said
yesterday that any תענית taanit *ta'anit* that you were not מקבל מבעוד
יום mib'od yom. *mekabel mibe'od yom* isn't a תענית taanit *ta'anit*. So
the idea that you need a קבלה kabbala *kabbalah* and to that
gives the weight to what you're doing transforms what you're doing to
just self-denial into some status of a תענית taanit *ta'anit*, שמואל *Shmuel*
said yesterday that you needed it from the previous day which exactly
fits the concept of נדר neder. *neder* and קבלה *kabbalah* and obligation.
So it's hard to understand this version of שמואל *Shmuel*, but we're
now going to move into a next version of שמואל *Shmuel* which
is much more consistent with what we saw yesterday.
But why does he say
משלם לצעו *m'shalem l'tzo*?
No, דלא סגי דלא משלם *d'lo sagi d'lo m'shalem*. Is it some
type of a vow that it wouldn't be enough if you didn't
pay it back? Okay so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this,
so okay but that doesn't really fit with what we know about
שמואל *Shmuel* so let's keep on reading. איכא דאמרי *Ika d'amri* some
say אמר רב יהודה אמר רב *Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav* לוה
loveh? אדם תעניתו ופורע *loveh adam ta'anito upore'a*, again you can borrow
against it and pay it back. כי אמריתה קמיה דשמואל *Ki amritai
kammei d'Shmuel* when I said it in front of שמואל *Shmuel* says
רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* because he first learned from רב *Rav* and
then from שמואל *Shmuel*, אמר לי *amar li* he said to me
פשיטא peshita *Peshita*, of course! לא יהא אלא נדר neder *Lo yehei
ela neder*, it shouldn't be any different. If somebody takes a vow,
can't he pay it the next day and the following, ליומא אחרינא?
So, נדר מי לא מצי בעי לשלומי ומיזל למחר ליומא אחרינא? neder
mi lo matzi bayei lishlumei umeizeil lemachar leyoma achrina? If somebody takes
a vow, can't he pay it the next day or the following?
So this is the same type of a saying. Okay, so what?
Also pretty shocking.
That he says פשיטא or that he says you can pay up
a vow on a different day? Yeah, that's the thing that's
shocking.
Exactly, exactly. So that's the thing that's funny too, meaning, okay, this
works much better with what we know about שמואל. There's a קבלה
מבעוד יום mib'od yom, and the קבלה transforms it from צירי נפשיה
tzirei nafshei into a תענית taanit? that it is some sense of
a vow. But again, taking for granted that you can pay up
a vow on a different day. Now, I do need to say
that there are two types of נדרים. nedarim. There is the נדר
neder of the תורה, Torah which is really what this much sounds
like it's much more similar to, like the נדר neder, of יעקב
אבינו. Yaakov Avinu. וידור יעקב נדר לאמור אם יהיה אלהים עמדי ושמרני
בדרך הזה אשר אנכי הולך, Vayidor Yaakov neder lemor im yiheye Elokim
imadi ushmarani baderech hazeh asher anochi holech, and you know, then וכל
אשר תתן לי עשר אעשרנו לך, vechol asher titten li aser aserenu
lach, האבן הזאת אשר שמתי מצבה יהיה בית אלהים. Ha'even hazot asher
samti matzeva yiheye beis Elokim.
So that's a basically a promise to do something. And you know,
God then appears to יעקב, Yaakov, right, in בית אל, Beis El,
and he's in בית
לבן Beis Lavan and says it's time to be משלם your נדר.
neder. Right? So there's an idea you could pay, okay, you said
you were going to do it. Did he do it the exact
moment or whatever? There's an idea of doing something, and it's not
exactly fixed in a particular day, it's more about the action and
the religious act that you're going to do. Okay? And maybe it
is more about like and the גמרא Gemara. talks about נדרי מצוה
nidrei mitzvah like a person says, I'm going to learn a hundred
דף by such and such a day, or here's an example, I'm
going to learn these משניות mishnayos for somebody's שלשים. shloshim. Okay? So
here's an interesting question. You didn't get it done by the שלשים.
shloshim. Is there still an idea to do it and are you
still to some degree מקיים mekayeim your נדר neder בדיעבד bedieved if
you missed that deadline? Because at the end of the day, the
idea really was just to do this religious act and the exact
date you set wasn't doesn't exactly determine if you're over on your
נדר neder. or not. You know, we learned in ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah the whole idea of בל תאחר, bal te'acher, but nevertheless, you
know, that the date is not all determinant, at least not having
missed that one day. That's at least the context in which something
like this fits. However, there's another idea of a נדר, neder. which
is the rabbinic idea of a נדר. neder And the rabbinic idea
of a נדר neder is transforming the halakhic status of a thing,
not accepting a personal obligation. So basically you say, all פירות peiros
in the world are forbidden to me, like you know, and you
make them actually an object a forbidden object, not a שבועה. shvuah.
שבועה Shvuah is about things you will or won't do. This is
about the status of things. This fruit is דבר אסור davar assur
to me. And you can do that through your vow. It's like
the way you can sanctify objects through your vow, you can make
them forbidden through your words. That's the rabbinic idea of a נדר.
neder That idea does not seem appropriate by תענית. ta'anit Now some
people want to fit it into that and speak about that what
you're transforming is the day. You're taking this day, Sunday, Tuesday, and
the same way you can make a fruit דבר אסור, davar assur,
you made this day a דבר אסור, davar assur, like a forbidden
thing to get benefit from, or you transformed it into a יום
תענית. yom ta'anis. The same way you can make yourself, for example,
into a נזיר nazir or an animal into a קרבן, korban, you
can make the day into a יום תענית. yom ta'anis. Alright, that's
the rabbinic idea of נדר. neder That doesn't work so well. That
doesn't fit in the idea of paying up, because you changed the
status of Tuesday. You didn't create a personal vow. So this seems
to work much more in this biblical idea of נדר neder which
the rabbis acknowledge and call נדרי מצוה. nidrei mitzvah. It's not the
rabbinic idea of נדר neder, but it's the biblical one. And therefore
that seems to be the idea here. You've created a personal obligation
to do a type of a מצוה mitzvah act or to give
something to God, presumably what you're giving to God is your fasting,
you know, that's the thing you're giving, and therefore the date maybe
is not so critical and בדיעבד bedieved you can pay that נדר
neder up on a different day. So maybe it was a little
late paying up the נדר neder. but you're paying it up on
a different day.
Okay. What's the difference between this Torah's concept of a נדר neder
and a שבועה? shvuah?
Yeah, so a שבועה shvuah is about taking the name of God
and if you don't do it you have like you're sort of
caught calling on God as your witness, so by not doing it
you are doing actually like that's why לא ינקה ה׳ את אשר
ישא את שמו לשוא. lo yenakeh Hashem es asher yisa es shemo
lashav.
It's a type of oath.
It's an oath. Right, a נדר, yeah, could be to give to
God but it's about accepting a binding personal obligation.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara but anyway this is very important,
the concept of נדר by תענית. ta'anit, And here שמואל takes it
for granted that it's a type of a נדר. Okay. רב יהושע
בריה דרב אידי איקלע לבי רב אשי. Rav Yehoshua brei deRav Idi
ikla levei Rav Ashi. רב יהושע Rav Yehoshua the son of רב
אידי Rav Idi came to the house of רב אשי. Rav Ashi.
עבדו ליה עגלא תילתא, Avdu lei egla silsa, they made him this
עגלא תילתא egla silsa which is supposed to be the fanciest dish
that you've got in the גמרא. Gemara It's a calf either within
three years old or the third calf to its mother, very juicy
tender calf. Okay, so they made him this choice steak. אמרו ליה,
Amru lei, they said to him, and he wasn't eating it. So
they put this delicious steak in front of him and he didn't
touch it. אמרו ליה, Amru lei, they said to him, ליטעום מר
מידי, lita'om mar midi, taste a little bit of it. אמר להו,
Amar leho, he said, בתעניתא יתיבנא. beta'anisa yasivna. No, I'm on a
תענית. ta'anit Okay, we learned before that
רב יוחנן... Rav Yochanan... The students or whatever, the household members. לוזיף
מר ולפרע, lozif mar uleifrei, so borrow against it and pay it
back! You got such a juicy steak. Okay, you'll eat your steak
today, you'll do your תענית ta'anit on a different day. So and
like somebody once told me that they were like telling a non-Jewish
friend, like a Christian friend, about like, you know, how challenging it
was one שבת Shabbos they were running away or whatever, you know,
and they were going to, you know, they were running right up
against, you know, שקיעה, shkiya, what were they going to do? I
don't understand, why can't you just like, you know, get a dispensation
for that like one שבת Shabbos you like borrow against it or
something. All right, you give a little dispensation here, you know, you
go ahead, you eat today, eat the steak and you'll pay up
tomorrow. What's the big deal?
So, לוזיף מר ולפרע להא דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב לוה אדם
תעניתו ופורע. lozif mar uleifrei l'ha d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav loveh
adam taniso uporea.
So apparently it was some of the various rabbis around the table
that were saying this to him. You can borrow against it. And
this is fascinating. This means you don't even need any special circumstance
to borrow against it. I'll pay, I'll do a תענית ta'anit one
day. I said I would do it today, but it's not really
about today, it's about doing a תענית ta'anit eventually so I can
do it tomorrow. So, what?
He did start the תענית?
ta'anit, He did, but that's the fascinating thing, that somehow it assumes
that even once you've started observing it, you can always choose to
pay it up on a different day.
Even if you've already said עננו Anenu in the...
yeah, so that's an interesting question too. I'll tell you what תוספות
Tosafos says about this in a minute.
But the language here was לוזיף? lozif?
To borrow. לוה.
But he also says לוזיף מר ולפרע? lozif mar uleifrei? לוזיף מר
ולפרע. lozif mar uleifrei.
Yeah, borrow and pay back. You're borrowing against it. So I'm going
to borrow today as a day of eating and I'll pay back
my fasting day tomorrow as a different day.
Is that the לשון lashon of זיזוף?
zizuf? No, no, no. לוזיף lozif is Aramaic for borrow.
And it's a complete synonym to לוה?
Yes. I don't know, maybe, I'm sure the grammar's different. I'm sure
the grammar might be different but I am telling you it's the
Aramaic of borrow.
All right, fine.
Okay. So אמר להו, amar lehu, he said to them, תענית חלום
הוא. tanis chalom hu. No, no, no, it's a fast because I
had a bad dream. And that I got to do right away
to fix the dream because I'm afraid about what the dream portends.
דאמר רבה בר מחסיא אמר רב חמא בר גוריא אמר רב יפה
תענית לחלום כאש לנעורת, d'amar Rabba bar Machasya amar Rav Chama bar
Gurya amar Rav yaffa tanis l'chalom k'esh l'neores, לנעורות l'neoros I guess.
A fast is good for dream like fire to flax. You have
this dream, you want to counteract it, if you fast, it'll burn
it up the same way fire, you know, takes, you know, burns
up flax like instantaneously. So, but, ואמר רב חסדא ובו ביום, v'amar
Rav Chisda u'vo bayom,
you got to fast on the following day if you want it
to counteract the power of the bad dream. ואמר רב יוסף, v'amar
Rav Yosef, and that's so much the idea of doing it the
next day that רב יוסף Rav Yosef says ואפילו בשבת, v'afillu b'Shabbos,
that if you can have a תענית חלום tanis chalom on שבת
Shabbos because of the importance of doing it the next day in
order to negate the bad dream. So therefore I can't pay this
one up. If I want this to be efficacious for a תענית
חלום, tanis chalom, I got to do it today. So anyway the
גמרא Gemara. just ends by saying מאי תקנתיה, mai takantay, and if
you fasted on שבת Shabbos because you needed to in order to
counteract the bad dream, but you did something wrong, you violated the
obligation to eat on שבת Shabbos and have עונג שבת, oneg Shabbos,
so how do you fix that problem? ליתיב תעניתא לתעניתא. leisiv tanita
l'tanita.
So now you have to make another fast to make up for
the fast that you did on שבת Shabbos which was done incorrectly,
which a little bit echoes the idea of paying up a fast,
right? But here you're sort of paying
up the eating, you know, it's like the funny way you... the
way you pay up the eating on שבת Shabbos that you didn't
do is through sitting a fast. It's almost like the parallel of
eating on ערב יום כפור erev Yom Kippur that counts as a
fast, so here fasting on a different day other than שבת, Shabbos,
you know, in a way you could say it gives like sanctity
to the day. And I should point out that the whole theme
here by תענית יחיד, tanis yachid, although the other day we had
the whole sort of raising serious questions about the religious value of
תענית יחיד tanis yachid when it's not done in the context of
תענית ציבור ta'anit tzibur and not done in the context of a
communal issue like lack of rain, but my own personal religious practice,
we raised serious questions. Here it's taken for granted that this is
a meaningful and a good religious act. The idea that the idea
of a נדר is relevant to it, right? If I said that
I'm going to take a vow that I'm going
to self-flagellate, wouldn't say well, you can pay that vow up on
a different day. What makes it a vow as opposed to just
a stupid thing to be doing? So obviously the idea that it
puts it in this נדר מצוה neder mitzvah category, you know, is
significant in terms of that earlier discussion. And the idea again that
fasting on a different day makes up for the fact of what
I did wrong on שבת, Shabbos, the fact that I fasted, how
does that correspond? But if you think, well, the idea that eating
on שבת Shabbos gives it,
you know, עונג שבת oneg Shabbos gives it special sanctity, special קדושה
kedusha reflects the special nature, we replace the
special identity of שבת Shabbos that's given through eating to make another
day a special religious day through turning it into a fast day.
That's one way of thinking about this idea. So anyway again it
is interesting the way this גמרא Gemara. I think takes for granted
the religious power of fasts. fasting which was seriously questioned in an
earlier גמרא. Gemara In terms of the questions that was raised about
can you really just easily borrow and pay up, so תוספות Tosfos
questions it, although that seemed to be the מסקנא maskana of the
גמרא. Gemara. If you look at תוספות Tosfos דאימטי מצער נפשיה, de-imati
mitzare nafshai, תוספות Tosfos says he reads the earlier discussion before where
it says that if you're able to do it, do it, if
not not, to qualify this idea of borrowing. He says ובשום הכי
קאמר שמואל דלווה תעניתא ופורע u-vshum hachi ka amar Shmuel de-loveh taanita
u-porea דווקא היכא דלא מטי מצער נפשיה, davka heicha de-lo mati mitzare
nafshai, only if you're finding it impossible are you allowed to borrow
and pay
back, או היכא דמטי מצער נפשיה לא מצי לילוות תעניתא. o heicha
de-mati mitzare nafshai lo mati lilvos taanita. Okay, והכי מסתקנא. ve-hachi mastikna.
Now again, I don't see how he reads that in the גמרא
Gemara, because the whole story with the steak did not seem like
לא מטי lo mati unless you really have a... yeah, I know,
I get it. Right, exactly. והרי ve-harei and here's the other point,
מסופק בדבר mesupak ba-davar אם יכול ללוות ולפרוע היכא דקיבליה כבר להתענות
ולהתנדב חצי היום או רביע היום. im yachol lilvos u-lifro'ah heicha de-kablei
kvar lehit'annot u-lehitnadev chatzi ha-yom o re-via ha-yom. If you've already passed
breakfast or you've passed your noon meal, maybe you've already fully established
the day as a תענית ta'anit? and you can no longer borrow,
you've already established the nature of the day and he has a
question about that. So again, I don't know how that fits in
with the story about the steak, which seems to take it very
easily the idea of paying back a different day, but תוספות Tosfos
raises some serious and reasonable, you know, reservations. Okay, yeah, quickly, and
then we'll go on.
Yeah, just for the whole dream thing, if we're saying he needs
to do it right מבעוד יום.
mib'od yom Right, so a dream, dream is the one thing exception,
so a תענית חלום taanit chalom is the one thing that it
doesn't require the idea of מבעוד יום, yom, but then it raises
the question: how much is מבעוד יום central to creating it a
status of תענית ta'anit or the reverse? Maybe the power of counteracting
the dream doesn't require that it has the הלכתי halachic status of
תענית ta'anit. and therefore it doesn't just need, it's somehow that self,
you know, denial has some power, but again, how that works, I
don't know. Okay, but that's an excellent point.
So, yeah, they certainly did. Next משנה. Mishnah. Okay, so now it
went, it said, it didn't rain by י"ז מרחשון Yud Zayin Mar-Cheshvan
and therefore התחילו יחידים להתענות. hitchilu yechidim lehit'annot. It didn't rain by
ראש חודש כסלו Rosh Chodesh Kislev and הציבור מתחיל להתענות. ha-tzibbur matchil
lehit'annot. So I want to, and now we're going to say that
it still didn't rain, but I want to, I want to alert
you to a difference in language. So it's, the first thing we
saw is הגיע, higia, you know, י"ז מרחשון, Yud Zayin Mar-Cheshvan,
you know, לא ירדו גשמים lo yardu geshamim and the answer was
יחידים yechidim begin to do three fasts. Okay, then it was הגיע
ראש חודש, higia Rosh Chodesh, right, I don't think it says ראש
חודש כסלו, Rosh Chodesh Kislev, but anyway, that's the point, לא ירדו
גשמים lo yardu geshamim and ציבור tzibbur begins to fast and that's
three, and those three are just the daytime and nothing extra. Okay,
nothing extra. Okay, and now we're going to get to the more
severe ones, but look how it's introduced. Let's look at the משנה.
Mishna,
עברו אלו ולא נענו. avru elu v'lo na'anu. Those three were of
the ציבור tzibur passed and and they were not answered. So בית
דין גוזרין ג' תעניות אחרות על הציבור. Beis Din gozin gimmel ta'aniyot
acharot al ha-tzibbur. Now obviously these are communal fasts. אוכלין ושותין מבעוד
יום. ochlin v'shosim mib'od yom. Here if you want to eat and
drink it has to be before nightfall. This is a full day,
starting at the night. Okay, this is what's called a classic תענית
ציבור, ta'anit tzibur full, you know, full blow. אסורין במלאכה. asurin bi-mlacha.
Not only can you not eat, you can't do labor, you can't
work, which is fascinating. What does that have to do with תענית?
taanit We'll see in the
גמרא. Gemara וברחיצה ובסיכה ובנעילת הסנדל ובתשמיש המיטה. u-ve-richitza u-ve-sicha u-ve-neilat ha-sandal
u-ve-tashmish ha-mitah. Things we know from יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Bathing, anointing,
wearing shoes, and sex. So all the additional forms of, like, self-denial.
ונועלין את המרחצאות ve-no'alin et ha-merchatza'ot and you lock the the bathhouses,
which you should say is obvious if you can't do רחיצה, rechitza,
maybe you would think they shouldn't even be open for non-Jews. Anyway,
I'll talk about that in a minute. Okay, and that's what you
do, full-blown fast. עברו אלו ולא נענו. avru elu v'lo na'anu. Now
these three passed and they still weren't answered. בית דין גוזרין עליהם
עוד שבע. Beis Din gozin aleihem od shiva. By the way, all
these fasts are Monday-Thursday-Mondays. So that's the calendar for them. Okay, it's
not giving dates, but figure it out, it's the following Monday-Thursday-Monday. בית
דין Beis Din says seven more fasts, which is
Monday-Thursday-Monday-Thursday-Monday-Thursday-Monday. שהן י"ג תעניות על הציבור. she-hein yud-gimmel ta'aniyot al ha-tzibbur. The
sum total is thirteen. Three before, before they were full-blown, three, and
seven. Okay. הרי אלו יתרות על הראשונות. harei elu yiterot al ha-rishonot.
These last seven are more expansive than the earlier ones. שבאלו מתריעין.
she-be-elu matri'in. First of all, you blow the שופר. shofar. Okay, these
are really like, oh my god, things are getting to be in
a very, very potentially like, you know, tragic, drastic situation. ונועלין את
החנויות. ve-no'alin et ha-chanuyot. You lock up the stores. Okay, interesting, right?
Before it was anyway אסור במלאכה, asur bi-mlacha, but here somehow there's
a public aspect of locking the stores.
ובשני, u'v'sheni, now on Mondays, מעטין עם חשכה, meattin im chashecha, as
it's getting close to dark, you know, people need to buy their
food for their breakfast and they need to buy food for tomorrow,
so you a little bit ease up a little bit towards night
in terms of like you allow the store, people to come to
the store. This is about the store. We'll see about this. ובחמישי
u'v'chamishi and on Thursdays, where you need people to start needing to
buy food for שבת, Shabbat, מותרין מפני כבוד השבת, mutarin mipnei kvod
haShabbat, then you allow also person you know people to buy stuff
for the sake of כבוד השבת. kvod haShabbat. So that's a little
leniency around the stores, which we'll get to, which we'll get to,
but that's parenthetical. The שוק. shuk. The חנויות. chanuyot. Okay. Now, so
before we get to the next part, I want to, I want
to point out to, right, the difference. This is הגיע ולא ירדו
גשמים. higia v'lo yardu geshamim. Right, so natural things didn't happen, it
didn't rain, we're responding to the absence of rain. Okay, so this
is, there's no rain.
We need, we need rain!
So you fast. Here is, right, here
is עברו אלו ולא נענו. avru elu v'lo naanu. So here the
problem is we're responding to no rain. Here what we're responding to
is why we're responding to here—God's not—right,
God isn't answering us. Right, God isn't answering us. It's a different
type of a response, okay, of a, you know, of a reaction.
And by the way, the נענו naanu is because you have been
undergoing a תענית Ta'anit
and you were hoping for the answer. Right, you wanted your תענית,
Ta'anit, you wanted to be answered. Yeah, and it wasn't, your תענית
Ta'anit was supposed to get God to answer, and God isn't answering.
You were in the עינוי inui of the תענית ta'anit and you
wanted God, but you were doing the תענית ולא נענו, ta'anit v'lo
naanu, you didn't get the result of God answering. Okay, so here
we're dealing not just with a physical crisis, with a material, like,
economic crisis, we're dealing with a religious crisis. Spiritual, right, why isn't
God answering? Okay, and that's an importance about the shift. And the
halakhic implication, one minute, is again three days, but here it is
full blown. And this is what's, this is the classic תענית ציבור.
ta'anit tzibur. This is full blown, which is night before and all
the extra stuff.
Seven days, right?
Yes, first three, and then if that, then you've got seven days.
And also, creations, right, and also full blown, and this also has
the idea of the חנויות, chanuyot, of the stores are locked. You
close the stores. And the other thing I do want to point
out, and we'll get to this in the גמרא, Gemara, is the
idea of not having the stores open and not having the מרחצאות
merchatzot open, but on the one hand it's logical, you can't bathe
and you can't do מלאכה. melacha. I mean, if you couldn't do
מלאכה melacha starting here, then of course the stores are going to
be closed. But the point still is, no, maybe, you know, maybe
we'll make technical distinctions, you know, under certain circumstances you can do
it, etc.
You know, לכבוד שבת, l'chavod Shabbat, this is not really a מלאכה,
melacha, but the public closing of it is a way of a
giving of a public expression to what is happening. Right? The whole
street is different. Not only the individual behavior. You walk out, right,
in the street, like you walk out in ירושלים Yerushalayim on שבת,
Shabbat, or you walk in some, you know, you feel the day,
you feel the nature of the day. So the bathhouses are closed,
all the stores are closed. There's a profound aspect of the, sort
of, of this being, and this, why this is called תענית ta'anit
ציבור, tzibur is not just because it is full blown, but because
this has the real public aspect to it. Okay, and there's a,
and this is everything and that's really what we're going to see
first thing in the גמרא Gemara is that the, you know, is
the way in which once we are dealing with this, like, religious
crisis and, you know, then, then really is something that the whole
ציבור tzibur is really coming together and there's an impact, you know,
a communal impact on what's happening. Yes.
Please. So with regard to the closing of the מרחצאות merchatzot and
the stores—yeah—is that a public obligation? Is this a regulatory obligation or
is this just individual store owners?
No, it seems to be public and
regulatory. Right? The language is, what's the language of, נועלין noalin in
the plural, I think. Well, no, before it was אסורין assurin and
אוכלין, ochlin, so I can't be מדייק medayek anything from the plural.
But I do have a sense, and we'll see in the גמרא,
Gemara yes, that it does seem to be like, as you framed
it, regulatory, like communal obligation, not individual.
Is there any place where it's put
into, you know, historical record of this?
Yeah, we will find actually in the משניות Mishnayot some discussions. I
don't know if they're highly detailed, but we do find some discussions
of these things. So, yeah.
Could you say a little more on the second question? Could you
say a little more about the distinction between rain and answers? What
are the other
drop-down in the drop-down menu, what are the other answers in addition
to rain?
Oh, how would God answer us if it weren't through rain?
I'm not sure that in this context we're seeing any other possibility
of answers or
not. You call up your parents because you want your kid, for
instance, call up your parents because you need them to send you
some money in camp or whatever it is. So the first two
weeks they're not answering, they're really annoying because you need the money.
After a while, you start wondering what does this say about that
my parent isn't responding to me? What does it say about the
relationship? So I'm not sure there's another form of answering or not
answering, it's the question about what you're reading into, what the problem
is that you're identifying. So maybe God isn't being so responsive here,
but it hasn't yet reached a pass that you have to really
start worrying about the relationship.
You've got to תענית Ta'anit a little more because you need the
rain. Here, you've got to start worrying about the relationship. So I
don't think that there's another version of it. I think the question
is how are you responding to what it all means? All right,
so let's keep on going. It says like this. It says: Now,
עברו אלו ולא נענו. avru elu velo na'anu. Now the whole thirteen
have passed and you haven't gotten response. So ממעטין במשא ומתן, mema'atin
bemasa umatan, you decrease
the amount of business you're doing; בבנין ובנטיעה, bebinyan uvineti'ah,
building things and planting things;
באירוסין ובנישואין, be'erusin uvenisu'in, betrothals and marriages; ובשאילת שלום בין אדם לחבירו,
uvishe'ilat shalom bein adam lachavero,
and greeting people and asking after their welfare.
Does that sound like anything to people? Some of these practices?
What? אבילות, aveilut, right. תשעה באב Tisha B'Av, and אבילות, aveilut, right.
כבני אדם הנזופים למקום. kivnei adam hanizufim lamakom. And that if you
needed it to be brought home, like people that are being rejected
by God. Okay. Now what's part? So you shift from תענית ta'anit
to אבילות. aveilut. What are you not doing in this period after
all those fasts haven't worked?
Fasting. Fasting isn't working. God is not answering. Fasting is not helping
it. And we've got to how are we going to deal with
this? We're not changing the situation. For whatever reason God's mad at
us and He's not responding. So how do we so what do
we do? We're not going to change His mind. We tried, that's
not working, so we have to just accept the situation and act
appropriately. And if God is rejecting us, we have to demonstrate our
sense of mourning over that reality of being rejected by God. So
here you're sensitive to why isn't God answering, but there's a hope
that you can work hard at it and get God to start
responding. Right? After all this passes, then you shift to what did
I do with my pen? Then you shift to אבילות. aveilut. So
you've got עברו אלו, avru elu, right, ולא נענו, velo na'anu, and
the answer is אבילות aveilut and נזופים. nizufim. Okay. So what about
I know
here you're rejected, God isn't answering, but maybe He will. Okay?
But maybe God will. Here it's accepting. You accept
the reality and that you're rejected. You're being rejected and you have
to act accordingly. So you switch to mourning. If that's the way
God feels and nothing is changing God's mind, then we have to
have the right religious response to show at least like we say,
what good is it going to do to demonstrate this? Well, to
not demonstrate this says we don't care about the fact that God
has rejected us. So if we really have internalized what all of
this means, then we have to demonstrate how tragic this is. It's
like what's the פסוק pasuk after הר סיני? Har Sinai? It's what
is it?
They removed עדיים מהר חורב. edyam mehar chorev. What's the verse?
What's the word? Anyway, but if God is telling us, "לא אעלה
בקרבך", lo e'eleh bekirbecha, we have to what does that mean? That's
terrible. We have to do something that demonstrates that we understand how
tragic that is and what state that we are in right now.
Yeah.
What about העינויים ha'innuyim on that third stage, on הסרת הסנדל hasarat
hasandal and תשמיש המיטה? tashmish hamitah?
In other words, it's no longer fast, but if it's an אבילות
aveilut model I would assume you're building on that type of?
Yeah, not necessarily. Meaning you have to identify what are the things
that demonstrate אבילות. aveilut. Some of them might, like an אבל avel
doesn't bathe and do סיכה, sichah, etc. and תשמיש המיטה. tashmish hamitah.
That is true. You know, others of them, but yes, then it
starts a question of figuring out the list of אבילות aveilut practices.
All
right, so the גמרא Gemara. says like this. Now והיחידים חוזרים
ומתענים. vehayechidim chozrim umit'anim. Now the יחידים yechidim are the ones that
don't give up and they are the ones that feel that there's
always a hope. A, they're more sensitive to the fact that things
might be going wrong before the problem starts fully. You remember the
יחידים yechidim started fasting as soon as there was an inkling that
something was wrong. And now they continue fasting even once there's a
sense like, all right, there's no point anymore. They're the ones that...
They have a heightened sense of the responsibility and maybe they can
still do some good. Maybe we can still hope that God will
respond. עד שיצא ניסן Ad sheyeitzei Nissan until Nissan is over. יצא
ניסן Yatza Nissan now it's already like five months later from when
you wanted it, and Nissan has now finished, has gone, so then
וירדו גשמים veyardu geshamim and finally it's rained? So oh it must
be wonderful, at least finally, finally? No, סימן קללה. siman kelalah. So
that if God waited that long then the rain at that time
actually it might actually be a קללה, kelalah, it might be hurtful
to the crops, but more than the question of whether it is
a קללה kelalah or not is that it's a סימן קללה. siman
kelalah. Is that by God giving it this late God is telling
you again a negative message. שנאמר הלא קציר חטים היום shene'emar Halo
katzir chitim hayom we'll see in the גמרא Gemara about the significance
of that פסוק. pasuk. Okay, the סימן קללה siman kelalah also echoes
back, right, the first משנה, Mishna. which is to ask for גשמים
geshamim during סוכות Sukkot is a- גשמים geshamim during סוכות Sukkot is
a סימן קללה, siman kelalah, right? So if גשמים geshamim are too
early while you're still in your סוכה Sukkah that's a סימן קללה,
siman kelalah, you might remember that. And here if it comes too
late it's סימן קללה siman kelalah and it's all about a סימן,
siman, again, not so much whether it's a קללה, kelalah, but that
it's a סימן siman that God is demonstrating something about the relationship.
Okay? So the interesting thing here is again also notice the יחידים
yechidim and their way of starting early and ending late, and maybe
not only do they have a heightened sense of responsibility but maybe
as we'll see in the story of חוני המעגל, Choni Hame'agel, maybe
there's some sense that the יחידים yechidim have a special relationship with
God that maybe they can still succeed where the ציבור did not.
Okay? So that's interesting about the role of the יחידים. yechidim. Let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: בשלמא כולהו אית בהו תענוג,
Bishlama kulehu it behu ta'anug,
we understand all the things you're adding, there's a sense of indulgence,
of pleasure, which fits into the concept of תענית, ta'anit which is
self-denial. רחיצה וסיכה ותשמיש המטה, Rechitza vesicha vetashmish hamitah,
all that makes sense. Well, I should have mentioned shoes too, but
okay. אבל מלאכה צער הוא, Aval melacha tza'ar hu,
you know, it's a- it's a pain to go to work. So
I guess it depends if you like your job. So not doing
מלאכה melacha is a vacation. Why is not doing מלאכה melacha a
meaningful thing to do on a תענית? ta'anit So אמר רב חסדא
אמר רב ירמיה בר אבא אמר קרא קדשו צום Amar Rav Chisda
amar Rav Yirmeyah bar Abba amar kra Kadshu tzom sanctify a fast.
Notice all the word of קדשו, kadshu, sanctify, we used that discussion
before by תענית ta'anit, to make up for שבת. Shabbat. Okay? קדשו
צום קראו עצרה. Kadshu tzom kir'u atzarah. קראו? Karu? קראו. Karu. I
think it's קראו. kir'u. קדשו צום קראו עצרה. Kadshu tzom karu atzarah.
קראו. Kir'u. All right, got to exact the word. קדשו צום קראו
עצרה. Kadshu tzom kir'u atzarah. Sanctify a fast day, call a day
of gathering. אסיפו זקנים, Ispu zekenim, gather the elders. So right there
in that פסוק pasuk and that's central is that a fast day
is not just a lot of individuals inflicting suffering on themselves, but
it has something about the community coming together and owning what's going
on and working on responding to what's going on. So כעצרת, ke'atzeret,
like עצרת, Atzeret, which is שבועות Shavuot or in the תורה Torah
שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeret. מה עצרת אסור בעשיית מלאכה אף תענית אסור
בעשיית מלאכה. Mah Atzeret assur be'asiyat melacha af ta'anit assur be'asiyat melacha.
The same way you don't do מלאכה melacha on a יום טוב,
Yom Tov, you don't do מלאכה melacha on a תענית. ta'anit, Okay?
So which means again, the point being and again in addition to
the idea of like the sanctity and the קדושה kedusha of the
day, it's a special day, is the idea of by not doing,
you know, מלאכה, melacha, again it gets at this public aspect, you
know? You are forcing everybody to stop their daily activities, reflect on
what's going on today, and also to come together. You're not distracted,
you're not going somewhere else to work, we're all going to get
together and דאוון. daven. Okay? So it's an opportunity for a public
sort of, you know, observance of the day and owning what's going
on. So
אי מה עצרת מאורתא אף תענית נמי מאורתא. Ei mah Atzeret me'orta
af ta'anit nami me'orta. One minute though, יום טוב, Yom Tov, שמיני
עצרת Shemini Atzeret or שבועות Shavuot begins the night before. So why
don't we say that this also begins the night before? Now the
thing is it does begin the night before, right, because these extra
three do begin the previous night. But so how do you- what
does it mean that it's not the night before? So רש"י Rashi
says,
you know, the גמרא Gemara hasn't spelled it out, but the גמרא
Gemara will say later that the איסור מלאכה issur melacha only begins
in the day. So why? It's not in the משנה. Mishnah But
that we're going to say later. So why here, why doesn't the
איסור מלאכה issur melacha already begin the night before? So אמר ליה
זעירא לדידי מיפרשא לי מיניה דרבי ירמיה בר אבא. Amar lei Ze'ira
lididi mefarsha li minei de-Rabbi Yirmeyah bar Abba. It was explained to
me in the name of רבי ירמיה בר אבא Rabbi Yirmeyah bar
Abba who was the one who quoted the פסוק. pasuk. אמר קרא
אסיפו זקנים דומיא דאסיפת זקנים. Amar kra ispu zekenim dumya de-asifat zekenim.
So the idea of calling- קראו עצרה kir'u atzarah calling a day
of gathering which we're also reading as making it a יום טוב
Yom Tov as it were is like the next part of the
gathering of the elders. מה אסיפת זקנים ביום. Mah asifat zekenim bayom.
The same way you gather the elders in the day, you know,
at night everybody's in their house, so obviously if you're going to
do a public gathering it's going to take place in the daytime.
אף התם נמי ביום. Af hatam nami bayom. So now it doesn't
literally mean the fasting, because we're talk- but it means the non-doing
מלאכה, melacha, this aspect of it also takes place in the day.
during the יום, during the day. So again, this idea that it's
all about creating the special aspect of the day, you know, in
the tragic sense and getting everybody together and having a public experience
of it, that people aren't going to their works, the whole day
has transformed and everybody is going to get together. So and that's
דווקא davka the getting together occurs in the day, so that's why
the איסור מלאכה issur melacha as opposed to everything else only begins
in the day, everything else begins the night before. So the גמרא
Gemara says ואימא מטיהרא, Ve'eima mitihara, well, maybe it should be like
noon time, like today we're getting together at noon. Noon is a
good time to get people together, everybody, so why do how do
you know you do it first thing in the morning? So אמר
רב ששת בריה דרב
אידי Amar Rav Sheishet brei deRav Idi מסייע ליה לרב הונא mesayei
lei leRav Huna דאמר רב הונא da'amar Rav Huna מצפרא כינופיא, mitzaphra
kinufya,
the gathering should take place in the morning, like you get people
together, you do it first thing in the morning. So I don't
know if that exactly answers it, but okay, that's the way it
is, it's a good time to get people together. היכי עבדי, Heichi
avdi, how do you do it? How do you structure your day
on a יום תענית? yom taanit? אמר אביי מצפרא עד פלגא דיומא,
Amar Abaye mitzaphra ad palga deyoma, from first thing in the morning
until noon מעיינין במילי דמתא, me'aynin bemilei demata, we look into matters
of the city. Now, what does that have to do with anything?
Like sometimes מילי דמתא milei demata means like do we, you know,
who's, you know, who's transporting our water, and are people paying their
taxes, like what does that have to do with anything? So you
have a town hall meeting? So if you look at רש"י Rashi
what מילי דמתא milei demata is, רש"י Rashi says about eight lines
from the bottom דרישה וחקירה לבדוק במעשיהן של בני העיר אם גזל
וחמס בידיהן ומפייסין אותן, drisha vachakira livdok bemaaseihen shel benei ha'ir im
gezel vechamas bideyhen umefaysin otan,
maybe some people have been wronged and have been stolen from or
whatever, and we as a community have not righted certain wrongs. Okay,
now that is again powerful because that gets to the idea of
what are we going to do as a community respond to the
fact that God isn't answering, not just an individual, all of us,
God is seemingly angry with us as a community. Well, maybe we
have to be בודק למעשיהן, bodek lemaaseihen, maybe maybe we've done something
wrong, and let's see if there's some some rights that need wrongs
some rights that need wrongs wrongs that need righting,
you know, and maybe that will get us back, you know, in
good relationship. Now, I do want to say, though, again, and this
is a point that I've been making, you know, normally we think
oh תענית ta'anit is a spur of תשובה, teshuvah, if God isn't
answering it's because I sinned, I have to do תשובה, teshuvah, and
you could say, well, that's what's going on here, the community is
saying maybe we have to do תשובה. teshuvah. But I think there's
a big difference. תשובה teshuvah focuses on much more of an interior
process of that regret, you know, re you know, and and and
a commitment not to do it in the future, self-transformation.
Here we're talking much more about the pragmatic, you know, righting of
the wrongs, like somebody was robbed and stolen from, you know, whatever,
we didn't judge the person or we didn't correct something, we didn't
pay back somebody money we owe him, we're going to fix that.
Okay, doesn't mean that we're going through a whole process of of
קאפינג על חטא kopping al cheit and fixing things, so you know,
structural things so it's not going to happen again in the future.
I mean, that would be lovely if we did that, but again,
I don't think the emphasis here is תשובה. teshuvah. The emphasis is
much more immediate. It doesn't focus on sin and תשובה, teshuvah, it
focuses on the fact God is distant, if God is distant that
means something needs fixing, fix what needs fixing. So again, I just
think it's a much less of an of this interior process of
תשובה teshuvah and much more of, you know, fixing the problems. So
that's the for and at a communal level.
בין אדם לחברו? Bein adam lachaveiro?
Well, partly it's that like we don't start asking the way, you
know, מילי דמתא milei demata presumably does not include and thank you
for bringing that up like oh like we're not good enough at
שמירת שבת, shemirat shabbat, we gotta do better about fixing our עירוב,
eruv, or I mean, you know, maybe it does, but it doesn't
sound like it, not the way the phrase and the way רש"י
Rashi interprets it sounds like it's בין אדם לחברו bein adam lachaveiro
number one. But the other one was something even in terms of
בין אדם לחברו, bein adam lachaveiro, if I injured you so or
whatever I broke your, you know, I ran into your car, I
can pay, you know, if I say you know I never paid
you for that here's the hundred dollars I owe you, we wouldn't
say because I gave you the hundred dollars I owe for for
for running into your car means I've done תשובה teshuvah for it,
right? I mean, even if I was like, you know, if I
went ahead and I even intentionally went ahead and broke something of
yours, right? So and I paid you for it, I fixed the
problem, I fixed I corrected what was sort of wrong in terms
of the world was a little bit out of out of kilter
and I've fixed, you know, the balance of things, but I haven't
done תשובה, teshuvah, right? But it's not about my תשובה, teshuvah, it's
about fixing like what's out of balance, what's out of place. Is
that clear? I mean, even in בין אדם לחברו bein adam lachaveiro
you could talk about a תשובה teshuvah process or just about a,
you know, a justice problem, a restitution and making things right. Yeah,
exactly, exactly. So I do think there's a very different focus here.
Okay, so now it says מכאן ואילך mikan va'eilach from that point
onwards, so we're working as a community to figure out what we
got to do, fasting is not necessarily, you know, the answer to
everything, maybe this maybe it's an opportunity to come together and to
grapple with it together. So now that we're all together, we're going
to talk about what are the things we have to be working
and making things better as a community. Okay. מכאן ואילך Mikan ve'eilach
from that point on רבעא דיומא קרינן בספרא ואפטרתא. riv'ah deyoma karinan
besifra va'aftarta. So for a quarter of the day we're going to
read from the ספר תורה Sefer Torah and the הפטרה, Haftarah, so
maybe we'll do liturgy and maybe we'll do like also type of
religious reflection, because especially the readings you do are ones that cause
for like religious reflection.
מכאן ואילך Mikan ve'eilach and the last part we we pray. Okay,
quite fascinating. We've been talking all along about a תענית ta'anit and
its connection to prayer. Here it emphasizes that the heightened aspect of
prayer, you know, is when is at the end of the process.
First you try to, you know, fix things as it were before
you turn to the prayer, שנאמר Shene'emar as the verse says, ויקומו
על עמדם ויקראו בספר תורת ה' אלהיהם. Vayakumu al amdam vayikre'u besefer
torat Hashem Eloheihem. So there's actually a פסוק pasuk that talks about
this, רביעית היום revi'it hayom so they were reading from the תורה
for a quarter of the day,
ורביעיתם מתוודים ומשתחווים לפני ה' אלהיהם urevi'itam mitvaddim umishtachavim lifnei Hashem Eloheihem
and the last quarter they were, you know, saying confession and bowing
down and praying to God. So again it's quite fascinating, you know,
that the prayer here comes at the end. Like the first thing
is, you know, it's sort of like echoing the נביאים, Nevi'im, right,
in in the תענית, taanit right, you know, what's the פסוק pasuk
in ישעיהו Yeshayahu that we read on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? It's
הלוא זה צום אבחרהו התר אגודות מוטה, Halo zeh tsom evcharehu hattir
aguddot mota, you know,
so, you know, is this the type of fast I want? That
you keep on fasting and you're not correcting all of the ills
of the society? To make it a meaningful fast, it has to
transform how you're going about and how you're acting and the type
of a type of a community you are, right? And again also
there there's a lot of a בין אדם לחברו, bein adam lachaveiro,
you know, focus. So that's fascinating, until this we never would have
imagined it, you know. תענית taanit is with תפילה tefillah and that's
the emphasis of the משנה Mishna here. No, the first thing it
does is it gets us focusing on setting things right. Let's figure
out how we can set things right. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
now says איפכא נמי Ipcha nami maybe I should reverse the order?
First start praying, right? So no, לא סלקא דעתך, Lo salka datach,
that doesn't make sense, you know, דכתיב dechtiv the verse says, ואלי
יאספו כל חרד בדברי אלהי ישראל על מעל הגולה ve'elai ye'asefu kol
chareid bedivrei Elohei Yisrael al ma'al hagolah and
they gathered to me about the, you know, about the trespass, you
know, in the exile all about all the sins that they had
and the intermarriage and all that and we to that was like
the whole focus initially, דכתיב udechtiv and then it says after all
that focus on מילי דמתא milei demata what's wrong communally, although again
there David going back to your question I think some of that
there was intermarriage and religious sin and not only בין אדם לחברו
bein adam lachaveiro
but it says there ובמנחת הערב קמתי מתעניתי ובפרשי כפי אל ה'
uvminchat ha'erev kamti mita'aniti uvfarsi chapai el Hashem
and only in the afternoon did I then not get up from
my fast meaning meaning stop fasting but no like I shifted gears
and brought, you know, and cried out to God. There's an interesting
line in רש"י Rashi here, רש"י Rashi says if you look about
10 lines down, ובמנחת הערב קמתי מתעניתי, uvminchat ha'erev kamti mita'aniti, רש"י
Rashi says לא שמתענה עד המנחה ואחר כך אוכל. lo shemit'aneh ad
haminchah ve'achar kach ochel.
It doesn't mean I stopped eating, I stopped fasting I started eating.
אלא לומר Ela lomar מצר נפשיה ובקריעיי mitzara nafshei uvkeri'ai in the
from the midst of my, you know, my suffering and my
rending garments, דאם אני קורא בבגדי ובמעילי de'im ani korei bevigdai uvme'ilai
and with my rent garments, הייתי מתפלל hayiti mitpallel I prayed in
that state, כדי שאתרצה kedei she'etratzeh in order that God would find
favor. Which speaks again to the relationship of תענית ta'anit and תפילה,
tefillah, that praying in a state of, you know, suffering and being
miserable and owning the tragedy is a way of basically saying God
should listen to our prayers. Look how miserable are we are, look
how we understand what it means that you're not answering to us,
have compassion on us, you know, recognize this state we're in. So
I think that's important in terms of the intersection of the two,
but what's more important in terms of the larger גמרא Gemara here
is that the focus the fasting comes at the end. The focus
first comes on, you know, fixing what they are doing. You know
and again one of the things we'll hear, right, that the דרשן
darshan says when they have the public fast is, what does it
say by אנשי נינוה? Anshei Ninveh? It doesn't say וירא את שקם
ותעניתם, vayar et sakkam veta'anitam, it says וירא כי שבו מדרכם הרעה.
vayar ki shavu midarkam hara'ah.
Okay, so again maybe it is getting a little bit closer to
the תשובה teshuva idea and the פסוקים pesukim here by עזרא Ezra
are are more, you know, going back to David's question not just
בין אדם לחברו bein adam lachaveiro but also about בין אדם למקום
bein adam lamakom or you might want to say בין אדם לציבור,
bein adam latzibur, the impact of having all this intermarriage and the
communal, but nevertheless it's the community taking responsibility for fixing things and
fixing their relationship with God which has to do with fixing perhaps
the ways they are acting as a community and again I'm not
so sure that I associate this exactly with the nature we tend
to focus about the interior process of תשובה. teshuva. Okay, so let's
continue. But again and that is the priority. Now the גמרא Gemara
continues. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, כל שהוא משום אבל kol
shehu mishum avel
now we have a nice discussion so we had a nice discussion
about this powerful other aspect of or prime being a primary aspect
of what the fast is. Now we're going to discuss different days
in which we have these
self-denials. the different types of meanings that they can have. Also the
end of the משנה mishna remind you is the אבלות avelut aspect.
So now we're going to look at things that are about תענית
and things that are about אבלות. avelut. כל שהוא משום אבל Kol
shehu mishum avel כגון k'gon תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av
anything type of an observance that is about mourning like תשעה באב
Tisha B'Av and אבל avel or actual אבלות, avelut, אסור בין בחמין
בין בצונן. assur bein b'chamin bein b'tzonen. You so although so you
cannot have not hot water or cold water. Even cold water is
forbidden. Meaning even though as an אבל avel you are permissible to
eat, but in terms of these other ways of demonstrating how miserable
you are or how detached you are from your daily activities, you
don't even have cold water. כל שהוא משום תענוג Kol shehu mishum
ta'anug but anything that the focus is not mourning but the focus
is pleasure and indulgence,
כגון תענית ציבור k'gon ta'anit tzibur like a תענית ציבור where you
don't do all these other practices also about bathing and anointing, but
the focus is not to demonstrate mourning, it's to demonstrate the suffering
לצער נפשיה l'tzayurei nafshei is the phrase the גמרא Gemara used, or
to or to embrace suffering. So in that type of a thing
בחמין אסור בצונן מותר. b'chamin assur b'tzonen mutar. It's only hot water
would be a תענוג ta'anug an indulgence, cold water would be permissible.
So here it seems to be that the line is that there's
things that are an indulgence that are conceived of as being like
pleasures, you know, also to do with what we're like habituated to,
right? Like the person, you know, who goes camping but needs the
necessities of life like running water and air conditioning. So you might
say running water's a necessity, air conditioning pleasure, but for some people
they're both pleasure, you know, they're both, you know, necessities, right? So
a lot of these things have to do with what we're sort
of accustomed to. But you understand the difference between a sense of
like not indulging in pleasures as opposed to accepting suffering. Of course
you might say that that it would be reversed. תענית is about
suffering. Eating is not an indulgence, it's a necessity. So maybe by
the תענית it has to be things and the גמרא Gemara phrases
לצער נפשיה, l'tzayurei nafshei, right? So maybe אבלות avelut the problem should
more be a one about indulgence. But it's so fascinatingly the גמרא
Gemara takes it the opposite way and says that, I mean maybe
because a תענית you're already fasting, so I don't know, but the
additional ones are more about as indulgences. You don't have to get
to the level where it's complete self-denial. Whereas for אבלות avelut it's
more strict. Now why is it more strict? You know, what's the
concept by אבלות? avelut? So you could go two ways. You could
say אבלות avelut is also about suffering, you know, somebody is demonstrating
how miserable they are because of the person has passed away and
the way they honor the dead and they demonstrate or they they
actualize their own feelings or whatever is by giving the expression to
it of look how miserable I am I'm not even indul- you
know, doing any of these types of things and and maybe it's
a way that's more even serious and more weighty than the תענית
because maybe it's so highly personal. You know, the other possibility of
thinking about it is just the sense almost like the, you know,
like the I mean maybe this isn't the best example, but sort
of like the נזיר Nazir who grows his hair wild and so
on. You know, אבלות avelut is removing yourself from society. So a
person is so caught up in their misery and suffering and the
loss that they can't even spend the time to do even like
the natural things that it requires to take care of their body.
They can't even bathe, they can't even shave, you know, so it's
like this intense sort of focus on the experience of the אבלות
avelut rather- so there's a difference as to whether it's about misery
and suffering, right? So we'll let a person eat, it's not a
תענית, you know, a guy's got a, you know, can't fast for
seven days and so on, but it's about giving full expression to
that and it's maybe in a heightened personal way, or maybe we
can think about even a different track about what it all means
by אבלות. avelut. The גמרא Gemara doesn't tell us what it means.
It just says אבלות avelut is more serious. If it's just about
תענית, then it's only a problem of hot water and not of
cold water, only a problem of hot water and not of cold
water.
And it's sometimes interesting by the way that an אבל avel is
not obligated to fast. Right, you could imagine an אבל avel being
חייב chayav to fast some part of the
day.
Right, right, but the גמרא Gemara says now again we'll see later
maybe that's seen as a concession, you know, and it is true
sometimes a person is sitting שבעה shiva the whole day, going to
my point about like, you know, and hasn't even thought about eating
the whole day, right? So it's like just it's not thinking about
and totally focused on- so look, we have a little bit about
that before about one of the powers of a תענית and a
תענית ציבור that it focuses the ציבור on what needs to be
focused on. But yes, it is interesting. Okay, רש"י Rashi says that
the reason אבלות avelut is more חמור, chamur, רש"י's Rashi language is
דאית ליה צערא טובא. d'it lei tzara tuva. Okay, so again that
highly personal sense of tragedy and suffering, but it does then raise
the issue about there is no תענית that is going on. Okay,
and maybe that's just a concession to, you know, basic needs as
we'll see a little bit later. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, אמר רבידי בר אבין אפנא נמי תנינא. Amar Rav Idi bar
Abin, afanan nami tanina. We I have support for this in our
משנה mishna that it's only an issue of hot water on a
תענית ציבור. Because the משנה Mishnah says ונועלין את המרחצאות, v'noalin et
hamerchatzot, you close the bathhouses. Bathhouses were steam houses. It was about
it being hot water.
that emphasizes that it's all about the hot water. So אמר ליה
אביי, Amar lei Abaye, Abaye said back to him, ואי בצינין אסור,
V'ee betzinin assur, look, let's what would you have wanted the משנה
Mishnah, to say assuming that you couldn't even use cold water on
a fast day? סוכרים את הנהרות מיבעי ליה? Socharin et hanaharot mibaya
lei? It should say you close up the rivers? Meaning, so you
can't do anything about the cold water, so it could be cold
water is אסור, assur, but it had nothing to say about the
cold water. So the גמרא Gemara says, סוכרים מיבעי ליה למיתני? Socharin
mibaya lei lemitni? Is that what you wanted it to say? So
אמר רב ששת בריה דרב אידי אבא הכי קא קשיא ליה. Amar
Rav Sheshet brei deRav Idi Abba hachi ka kashya lei. No, here
is what was his problem, here is what was his, you know,
what bothered him about the משנה, Mishnah. what he wanted to infer
from the משנה. Mishnah מכדי, Mikhdi, let's take a look, תנן אסור
ברחיצה. tenan assur birchitzah. It already says you don't bathe. נועלין את
המרחצאות למה לי? Noalin et hamerchataot lama li? Why add that aspect?
Isn't that a logical conclusion of being forbidden to bathe? So, אלא
לאו
שמע מינה, ela lav shma mina, it must be if it's repeating
it even though you could have figured that out, it's to underscore
that it's about hot water. בחמי אסור בצינין מותר. B'chami assur b'tzinin
mutar. Okay. I also said again, I think you can also read
into this the public aspect because, you know, it's like stores that
are open during the nine days, kosher restaurants that serve meat during
the nine days. It's like, you know, maybe somebody's a חולה, choleh,
maybe somebody whatever, there are reasons why somebody might have an exemption.
Maybe the minors wanted to go to the bathhouse. Okay, so there's
an aspect of making it a public observance. But anyway, nevertheless, the
גמרא Gemara wants to infer from the repetition that it's about hot
water. לימא מסייע ליה. Leima mesayei lei. Let's try to give a
proof to this that it's about that on the other days it's
about cold water and there's two things to prove. A, on things
of אבילות aveilut it's cold water, and B, on fast days it's
just hot water. Let's try to prove the cold water point. כל
חייבי טבילות טובלין כדרכן בין בתשעה באב בין ביום הכיפורים. Kol chayavei
tvilot tovlin kedarkan bein b'Tisha B'Av bein b'Yom HaKippurim. All people that
have to go to the מקוה mikvah and, you know, this isn't
talking about women, the focus, I mean it includes women, but the
focus here is other people that have a, you know, בעל קרי,
ba'al keri, other people that the day of going to the מקוה
mikvah falls out on תשעה באב Tisha B'Av or falls on יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, you go even on תשעה באב Tisha B'Av? and
on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. That's not the way we פוסקים, pasken,
but that's this position.
But now, why do you have to tell me you go on
תשעה באב? Tisha B'Av. יום כיפור Yom Kippur we'll bracket for now.
That's by the way notice that's one thing that's not discussed. We
have משום אבל mishum avel and משום תענית. mishum taanit. Which is
יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? יום כיפור Yom Kippur isn't אבילות, aveilus, but
is it just about a תענית or are there other aspects to
the identity of יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? Because יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
by the way, is אסור assur even in cold water. So in
our category, תענית is hot water and אבל avel is even cold
water. We should note that יום כיפור Yom Kippur is also forbidden
even in cold water, but that's maybe a third category. So we'll
just bracket יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, let's focus on תשעה באב. Tisha
B'Av, So, כל חייבי טבילה... kol chayavei tvilah... so במאי? b'mai? What
type of water are we talking about about going to the מקוה?
mikvah? אילימא בחמי, Eilima b'chami, if it's a nice heated מקוה mikvah
and that's the problem of going on תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av so
טבילה בחמי מי איכא? tvilah b'chami mi ika? Who gets her, where
do you get hot water for your מקוה? mikvah? שאובים נינהו, Sheuvim
ninhu, that would have to be drawn water because you heat it
up over fire and then you pour it into the מקוה. mikvah.
Now, you could say aren't there other ways to heat it up?
Okay, but anyway, and can't you pour it in and the מקוה
mikvah already has enough natural rainwater so adding extra water isn't a
problem, but anyway, the גמרא says let's assume we're not going to
the מקוה mikvah in hot water. אלא לאו בצינין, Ela lav b'tzinin,
we're talking about the מקוה mikvah is cold. וחייבי טבילות אין, V'chayavei
tvilot in, and the only people that can go to the מקוה
mikvah on תשעה באב Tisha B'Av are people that have to go
that day. אינש אחרינא לא, Inish achrina lo, a normal person no.
So it's pretty clear, the מקוה mikvah is cold water and there's
an exception for חייבי טבילות, chayavei tvilot, which shows that on the
general rule on תשעה באב Tisha B'Av and parenthetically יום כיפור Yom
Kippur is not even cold water. So אמר רב חנא בר קטינא
לא נצרכה אלא לחמי טבריה. Amar Rav Chana bar Katina lo nitzrecha
ela l'chamei Tverya. Maybe it's talking about a scenario
where your מקוה mikvah was the hot springs of טבריה Tverya and
was natural hot water. Maybe it's a scenario of hot water. So
the גמרא said, אי הכי אימא סיפא, ee hachi eima seifa, let's
look at the end. אמר רבי חנינא סגן הכהנים, Amar Rabbi Chanina
sgan hakohanim, and this is the way we פוסקין, paskin, כדאי הוא
בית אלהינו לאבד עליו טבילה בפעם אחת בשנה. kedai hu beit elokeinu
l'abeid alav tvilah b'paam achat b'shanah. So focusing on תשעה באב Tisha
B'Av. bracketing יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, look, the destruction of the temple
is a good enough reason to miss going to the מקוה mikvah
one day even if it's the right day. So you don't go
to the מקוה mikvah on תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av, So now, what's
the problem? ואי אמרת בצינין מותר, V'ee amart b'tzinin muttar, if there's
always an option of cold water on תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av? so
ירחץ בצינין. yirchatz b'tzinin. What is this big deal he says oh
it's got to be אסור assur on תשעה באב? Tisha B'Av. Just
go in a cold מקוה. mikvah. So it seems pretty clear there
are no options, that the problem is cold water. אמר רב פפא,
Amar Rav Papa, so Rav Papa says, באתרא דלא שכיח צינין. b'atra
d'la shchiach tzinin. No, maybe there is no cold מקוה, mikvah, maybe
the whole ברייתא braita is talking about a case where all you
have is hot water and that's the only option. Again, that's a
really big stretch. It makes it pretty clear that there's no options
of by going to the מקוה mikvah you're confronting the איסורים issurim
of תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av Either you say you go anyway or
you say like רב חנניה סגן הכהנים Rav Chananya sgan hakohanim that
you don't go, but it seems like you're going to run there's
no other option. So it's a very big stretch to limit the
משנה to hot water, the simple sense of the ברייתא braita but
the simple sense of this ברייתא braita seems to say very strongly
half of what was being said, that on תשעה באב Tisha B'av,
even cold
water. But we do know,
but this seems to, you know, sort of solidify the first half
or the second half, that things that are because of אבילות aveilut
and תשעה באב, even cold water. Whether things that are just because
of תענית are only hot water or not has not yet been
proven. Okay, so we will continue with this discussion and see about
hot and cold water tomorrow.